A Guide to the Loudoun County Public Schools Archeological Surveys, 1998-2013
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Loudoun County Public Schools Archeological Surveys, 1998-2013
Thomas Balch Library
M 097
1 cu. ft..
The collection consists of archeological investigations of properties under consideration as sites for new public school facilities in Loudoun County. One report is a history of desegregation in Loudoun County Public Schools and, in particular, Douglass Elementary School. The reports were commissioned by Loudoun County Public Schools, consultants, or developers.
Loudoun County Public Schools, Ashburn, VA.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Loudoun County Public Schools, Ashburn, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None
Historical Information
Cultural resource investigations are performed prior to the construction of public school facilities. The primary purpose of the reports is to locate and identify archeological sites, historic standing structures, and other cultural resources in order to determine their significance for eligibility for the National Register of Historic Places.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of archeological investigations of properties under consideration as sites for new public school facilities in Loudoun County. One report is a history of desegregation in Loudoun County Public Schools and, in particular, Douglass Elementary School. The reports were commissioned by Loudoun County Public Schools, consultants, or developers. The reports are organized chronologically. When possible, the name of the school built (or to-be-built) on the site has been included. The collection also contains a USB drive with electronic copies of the reports.
Arrangement
Chronological
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Loudoun County Public Schools Archeological Surveys (M 097), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Other Finding Aid
None
Related Material
Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA 1938-1971 (M 073), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Separated Material
None
Contents List
  - 1
    - Phase I Archeological Investigation at Belmont Plantation, Loudoun County, Virginia-DRAFT COPY by Cultural Resources, Inc., 1998
    - Phase I Archeological Resources Reconnaissance of the Red Cedar Parcel (Sycolin Creek Elementary School), Loudoun County, Virginia by William M. Gardner, Kimberly Snyder, Gwen Hurst and John Mullen, June 2001
    - Phase I Archeological Identification Survey of the Proposed Loudoun Valley Estates School Proffer Parcel, Dulles, Loudoun County, Virginia, prepared by The Ottery Group, Inc., Thomas Bodor, RPA (Principal Investigator), William Hoffman, RPA, April 2004
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the Circa 35 Acre Xerox Parking Property, Loudoun County, Virginia by Christine Jirikowic, Paw Jorgensen, and Gwen J. Hurst, December 2004
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the 4 Acre Property at 42827 Braddock Road (Michael J. Lunsford Middle School), Loudoun County, Virginia by Paw Jorgenson, June 2005
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the Circa 450 Acre Moorefield Station, Section II Property (Moorefield Station Elementary School), Loudoun County, Virginia by Brian Buchanan, September 2005
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the 80 Acre Harmony Elementary School Property, Loudoun County, Virginia by David Carroll and Jennifer Rakos-Simonson, January 2006
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the Circa 32-Acre Ticonderoga Brennan Property (J. Michael Lunsford Middle School), Loudoun County, Virginia by David Carroll, March 2006
    - Cemetery Delineation of an Unnamed Cemetery on the Ticonderoga-Brennan Property (J. Michael Lunsford Middle School), Loudoun County, Virginia, by Christine Jirikowic, April 2006
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the 102.4 Acre Western Loudoun Middle School Property, Loudoun County, Virginia by Christopher Shephard, May 2006
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the Circa 147 Acre Field Farm Property (Woodgrove High School), Loudoun County, Virginia by Stephanie Taleff Sperling and Elizabeth S. Paynter, June 2006
  - 2
    - Phase II Archeological Evaluation of Site 44LD1393 on the Fields Farm Property Loudoun County, Virginia by Brian Buchanan, Christopher Shepard, and Johna Flahive, November 2006
    - Phase I Archeological Investigation of the 99 Acre Lenah School Property, Loudoun County, Virginia by John Mullen, M.A. and David Carroll, July 2008
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the 97.16 Acre High School Number 7 (John Champe High School) and Future Elementary School Property, Loudoun County, Virginia by Kimberly A. Snyder, M.A. and David Carroll, December 2009
    - Desegregation in Loudoun County Public Schools, 1954-1970; Timeline of Events Associated with Douglass Elementary School (55 Plaza Street, SE, Leesburg); People Associated with Douglass Elementary School, 1954-1970 Prepared for Loudoun County Public Schools by Evelyn D. Causey, PhD and Julia Claypool, History Matters, LLC, Edna Johnston, Principal, April 30, 2010
    - Phase I Archeological Investigations of the 9.28 Acre Douglass Support Center Property, Leesburg, Virginia by Kimberly A. Snyder, M.A., July 2010
    - Additional Archeological Investigations of Off-Site Infrastructure Improvements for the Douglass Support Facility, Leesburg, Virginia by Kimberly A. Snyder, M.A., RPA and David Carroll, July 2010
    - The Farmwell Elementary School Property (20 Acres), Loudoun County, Virginia, Phase I Archeological Investigation Prepared by Craig Rose, M.A. and Tammy Bryant, M.A., April 2011
    - Grant Perkins Property (47 Acres) (Cardinal Ridge Elementary School), Loudoun County, Virginia, Phase I Archeological Investigation Prepared by Tammy Bryant, M.A., RPA and Andres Garzon Oeschle, June 2011
    - Site 44LD1594 (Farmwell Elementary School), Loudoun County, Virginia, Phase II Archeological Evaluation Prepared by Craig Rose, M.A., July 2011
    - Hovatter Property (Dulles South Area Middle School, MS-7), Loudoun County, Virginia, Phase I Archeological Investigation Prepared by John Mullen, M.A., RPA, David Carroll and Susan Grealy, June 2012
    - I, George Lee of Farmwell, Loudoun County, Virginia: A History of the Lees and the Farmwell Community Prepared by Craig Rose, M.A. and Boyd Sipe, M.A., December 2011, Revised October 2012, Second Revision January 2013
    - USB Drive 2013